<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of John Swinton, in relation to his father's pretended forfeiture upon pretext whereof, the estate of Swinton hath been unjustly possess'd by the late Duke, and this Earl of Lawderdale [sic], ever since the year 1660. With the reasons of reduction of the said forfeiture, now depending against the said Earl, at the instance of the said John Swinton, before the Parliament.</title>
            <author>Swinton, John, Sir.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170951</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51617744</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51617744</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02584)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2718:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of John Swinton, in relation to his father's pretended forfeiture upon pretext whereof, the estate of Swinton hath been unjustly possess'd by the late Duke, and this Earl of Lawderdale [sic], ever since the year 1660. With the reasons of reduction of the said forfeiture, now depending against the said Earl, at the instance of the said John Swinton, before the Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Swinton, John, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Swinton, John, --  Sir, fl. 1696 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Lauderdale, Charles Maitland, --  Earl of, d. 1691 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Forfeiture --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175164:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF JOHN SWINTON OF SWINTON, In Relation to HIS FATHER'S PRETENDED FORFEITURE: Upon pretext whereof, the Eſtate of <hi>Swinton</hi> hath been unjuſtly Poſſeſs'd by the late Duke, and this Earl of <hi>Lawder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> ever ſince the year 1660.</p>
            <p>WITH The <hi>Reaſons</hi> of <hi>Reduction</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> now Depending againſt the ſaid Earl, at the Inſtance of the ſaid <hi>John Swinton,</hi> BEFORE <hi>THE PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="case">
            <pb facs="tcp:175164:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175164:2"/>
            <p>THE Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> having, after the late King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Reſtauration, firſt entered to the <hi>Poſſeſſion,</hi> and then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a <hi>Gift</hi> of the deceaſs'd <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Eſtate, upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his being forfeited by a <hi>Committee</hi> of Eſtates, (for his being with the <hi>Engliſh</hi>) in the Year 1651. By which Right, and a ſupervenient Decreet of Forfeiture, pretended to be given againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> (for the ſame Crime) by the Parliament 1661. he had that <hi>intereſt</hi> and <hi>power</hi> in this <hi>Nation,</hi> to poſſeſs the ſaid Eſtate as long as he lived, and at his Death, to leave it in Succeſſion to his Brother this Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> who hath poſſeſſed it ever ſince. Albeit there was nothing could ever be made appear, to evince that there was any ſuch Forfeiture againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> in the Year 1651. but the pretended <hi>Extract</hi> of a Decreet <hi>in abſence,</hi> elicit from an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Clerk</hi> ten years after, of which there was never the leaſt War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant upon Record. And that as to any Forfeiture in the year 1661. there was only a <hi>Proceſs</hi> then intented, that not being inſiſted in, never came the length of a <hi>Sentence.</hi> But to ſupply this Defect, <hi>Swinton</hi> having objected it to the Duke of <hi>Lawderdale,</hi> the later end of the year 1673. there were Methods taken in the Month of <hi>January</hi> 1674. to procure <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes</hi> to be made up by a <hi>Clerk,</hi> as if a Sentence of Forfeiture had follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon that <hi>Proceſs</hi> 1661, and thereupon a Decreet was got extracted 13 or 14. years after. Tho this was thought ſo tickliſh a thing at that time, by the then Clerk Regiſter, as not daring to adventure upon it without <hi>extraordinary Precaution;</hi> he firſt dealt with the late Earl of <hi>Crawfurd,</hi> (who preſided in that <hi>Parliament,</hi> when the Chancellor was abſent) to ſign the Minutes, as in <hi>praeſentia Dominorum Parliamenti,</hi> albeit 13. years after that <hi>Parliament</hi> (at leaſt that Seſſion of it) was no more in <hi>Beeing:</hi> and then cauſed <hi>application</hi> to be made in behalf of the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> to the Lords of <hi>Seſſion,</hi> to give their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for extracting, what he was conſcious to himſelf was ſo <hi>unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably</hi> done.</p>
            <p>That part which the Earl of <hi>Crawfurd,</hi> (a Perſon of ſuch known
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175164:3"/>Honour and Integrity) was prevail'd with to have in ſo unjuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a Practice, his Lordſhip had the Juſtice to leave atteſted by him before he died, in a <hi>Miſſive Letter,</hi> all written with his own hand, and depoſited by him in the hands of the Lady <hi>Helene Sinclair</hi> his Daughter, to be delivered by her after his Death (as it punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was) to the deceaſs'd <hi>Swinton,</hi> to whom it was directed. Which Letter is conceived in theſe terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>TYNINGHAME</hi> 
                        <date>the 8 <hi>June,</hi> 74.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YE were pleaſed lately, both your ſelf, and by ſome others, to ſay, that I had done you an Injury in ſigning the <hi>Minutes</hi> of your <hi>Proceſs,</hi> eſpecially being out of all Imployment when I did it. I ſhould think my ſelf very unfortunate, if I did any thing <hi>willingly,</hi> to prejudge you or any Man alive. Therefore I ſhall tell the Truth (in point of <hi>Fact</hi>) now, not being able to ſpeak with you when ye deſired me. My Lord <hi>Regiſter</hi> ſent down a Servant to my Lodging in <hi>James Deans's</hi> Houſe, ſome day in <hi>January</hi> or <hi>February 74.</hi> and ſaid, If I were within, he would come and ſpeak with me. I bid his Man tell him, I was preſently going out, and ſhould call to him up the way. When I was near the length of Croſs, I met him in his Coach. I made mine halt, and went out, (as he did) to the <hi>Plain Stones.</hi> He told me I behoved to go to ſome <hi>Houſe.</hi> So we went to <hi>Patrick Steel's</hi> Houſe. where he took out a long <hi>Scroul,</hi> and ſaid, That was <hi>your Proceſs.</hi> I told him I knew nothing of it: it was ſo long ago, that I did remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nothing. He anſwered, There is the Chancellor's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, to what paſſed before he went to <hi>England;</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Meanning the Minute before the Articles, mentioned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</note> and I being <hi>Preſident</hi> after, behoved to ſign it: for it could not be preſented then, I going preſently to <hi>London.</hi> I firſt ſaid, Being out of all Office, I thought it <hi>unfit</hi> for me to do. Next I ſaid, ſome of the <hi>Minutes</hi> (as the <hi>Inditement</hi> was) were
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175164:3"/>of <hi>old</hi> Writ, and a great deal thereof <hi>new.</hi> He ſaid, Both were Mr. <hi>John Hay</hi> of <hi>Hayſtoun's</hi> hand, and he was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the <hi>Minutes.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Repreſentation I did it: and I have told you the naked Truth, upon my Honour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and I did it without end of advantage, or prejudice to any. But being preſsed to it as my Duty, I hope ye will believe this ingenuous Dealing, and keep no more prejudice or miſunderſtanding againſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your affectionate Servant, Crawfurd &amp; Lindeſay.</signed> Addreſſed on the Back, For John Swinton, Theſe.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>It might be thought ſtrange, why the Duke of <hi>Lawderdale,</hi> being a Man of ſuch Power during the late King <hi>Charles's</hi> Reign, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Title to be ſo defective as it was, ſhould not rather have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to have had the deceaſs'd <hi>Swinton</hi> truely forfeited, either by cauſing inſiſt in that Proceſs, intented before the <hi>Parliament</hi> 1661. or cauſing intent a <hi>new</hi> one; rather than to have had recourſe to ſuch <hi>indirect</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> Methods to ſupport a <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> Forfeiture, whereof there either was <hi>no</hi> Warrant upon Record, or whereof the Warrants upon Record were <hi>falſe.</hi> But the truth is, <hi>Swinton's</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken and detained Priſoner by the <hi>ENGLISH,</hi> in the year 1651. being all the ground there was for the Crime alledged againſt him at that time, for which he was pretended to be forfeited; and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that ſtate, till after the Fight at <hi>Worcester,</hi> and ſubjection of the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Nation to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> durſt not, for all his Power, adventure to put a Crime ſo calumnious, to the Trial of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> as knowing <hi>Swinton</hi> would have been able to have clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, and conſequently able to have recovered an Eſtate out of his hands, that he had got himſelf thus poſſeſſed of, and could not but be very loath to part with.</p>
            <p>The Letter writ by the Earl of <hi>Crawfurd,</hi> having been ſhown to the late K. <hi>Charles,</hi> and the intire matter of Fact repreſented to him, as it truely was; he in the year 1682. granted <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to the then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175164:4"/>Lord <hi>Chancellor</hi> and ſeveral other Perſons, to make Inquiry into the whole <hi>Procedure</hi> concerning the ſaid Forfeiture, and to inſpect the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of <hi>Parliament</hi> in relation to the ſame, and to make Report there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to His Majeſty. Purſuant whereunto, the Records of <hi>Parliament</hi> were inſpected. And as there was <hi>nothing at all</hi> found as to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Decreet of Forfeiture, in <hi>anno</hi> 1651. ſo as to that of <hi>anno</hi> 1661. <hi>all</hi> that was found, did (from <hi>ocular inſpection,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumſtances concurring with the Earl of <hi>Crawfurd's</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and even from the Records of Parliament themſelves) make it manifeſtly evident to be <hi>falſe.</hi> However, the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> had that influence upon thoſe, to whom the Trial of this Affair was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended at that time, as rendred the further Proſecution of the Commiſſion given them, ineffectual. Nor was <hi>John Swinton,</hi> who now repreſents his Father, nor his eldeſt Brother before him, in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to quarrel otherwiſe their Adverſarie's Title, ſo long as there ſtood pretended Decreets of Parliament in their way, of a Forfeiture (how falſe and groundleſs ſoever) againſt their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Thus the Eſtate of <hi>Swinton</hi> hath been unjuſtly poſſeſſed by the Duke of <hi>Lawderdale,</hi> and the Earl his Brother, for the ſpace of near 30 years: (for tho the Duke got his Gift of the pretended Forfeiture of that Eſtate, in the year 1661. yet he entred to the Poſſeſſion of it in the year 1660. eight Months before the Gift was granted.) During all which time, the true Proprietars have been debarred from acceſs, to an Inheritance tranſmitted to them from their Anceſtors, by an unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted Succeſſion of above 600 years. And for the Recovery where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, upon the preſent <hi>Revolution,</hi> this <hi>Swinton</hi> the Repreſentative of the Family, being to make Application to the PARLIAMENT now ſitting, as the <hi>Supreme Judicatorie</hi> of the Nation, and in order thereunto, having after the firſt <hi>Adjournment,</hi> intented a <hi>Reduction</hi> before the ſame, of the two pretended Decreets above mentioned, of his Fathers <hi>Forfeiture;</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Lawderdale,</hi> having been cited ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon by a Warrant of the <hi>Council,</hi> (the Signet not being open)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175164:4"/>and the Rents of the Lands by the Council's Order ſequeſtered in the Tennents hands during the <hi>Dependence,</hi> the REASONS of the ſaid <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> are here ſubjoyned.</p>
            <div type="reasons">
               <head>REASONS OF RED<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTION at <hi>Swinton</hi>'s Inſtance againſt the Earl of <hi>Lawderdale.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE PRETENDED DECREET OF THE COMMITTEE OF ESTATES, 1651. whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi>'s Gift is founded, cannot be reſpected as a Decreet and Doome of Forfeiture, and ought to be <hi>reduced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is a Decreet in abſence, not ſubſcribed by the Clerk Regiſter for the time, but by Mr. <hi>Thomes Henriſon,</hi> pretended to be Clerk to that <hi>Committee,</hi> from whom a pretended Extract thereof was elicit in the year 1661. ten years after, and whereof there is no Warrant extant in the Records of Parliament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though it laboured under no ſuch Defect; yet it being againſt ſeveral other Perſons, aſwell as the deceaſs'd <hi>Swinton,</hi> and particularly againſt one <hi>John Hume,</hi> accuſed and convict for betraying the <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> It bears an expreſs Declaration, <hi>That the King and Committee of Eſtates, for Reaſons and Conſiderations moving them, did restrict the Sentence and Puniſhment, to the Execution of the ſaid</hi> John Hume <hi>to the Death.</hi> Which clearly takes off the effect of the Sentence, as to <hi>Swinton</hi> and all the reſt, till it ſhould be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſidered</hi> by the King and Parliament.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the late CLAIM OF RIGHT, it is declared by the MEETING OF ESTATES, <hi>That the cauſing purſue and forfeit Perſons upon frivolous and weak Pretences, and upon lame and defective Probation, is contrary to Law.</hi> And it is evident, that this pretended Decreet proceeds upon moſt frivolous, weak, and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relevant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175164:5"/>Pretences. The Crime therein libelled againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> being, That <hi>be hawing a Charge in the King's Army, deſerted the ſame and went in to the Enemy, and had his frequent Reſidence with, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to the Enemy in the Town of</hi> Edinburgh, Cannongate <hi>and</hi> Leith, <hi>carrying has Sword about him.</hi> Which as libelled, was both irrelevant and calumnious. For he did not deſert the King's Army, but being Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenam-Collonel of a Regiment of Horſe under the King, and at that time his neceſſary Occaſions calling him over to his Houſe in the <hi>Merſe,</hi> he gave up his Commiſſion (as he, or any man in ſuch Circumſtances might lawfully do) and one <hi>Crawfurd</hi> of <hi>Crawfurdland</hi> was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly thereupon put in his Place. And as he croſſed the Water, (ſeveral Weeks, if not Months after he had thus quit his Charge, and <hi>Crawfurdland</hi> had got it) being intercepted by a Party of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and carryed to their General's Quarters; he was for ſome time detained there a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> and thereafter, upon his <hi>Parole,</hi> had liberty to go home. Which neither in Senſe, nor Reaſon, nor in the Conſtruction of Law, could be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood a <hi>deſerting</hi> of the King's Army, and <hi>going in</hi> to the Enemy. And that he <hi>reſorted</hi> to, and <hi>reſided</hi> with the Enemy in <hi>Edinburgh, Cannongate</hi> and <hi>Leith;</hi> was a moſt frivolous and abſurd Pretence, to infer the Crime of <hi>Treaſon.</hi> For theſe Places, and the greateſt part of the Southſide of <hi>Forth,</hi> being then under the Enemie's Power; it could infer no Crime, much leſs the Crime of Treaſon, againſt any who had occaſion for their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Affairs, to come where the Enemy was; that they reſorted to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, or converſed with them. For if that had been relevant, the moſt part of the Inhabitants of this ſide of <hi>Forth,</hi> might have at that time been forfeited upon the ſame ground. And certainly ſimple <hi>Converſe,</hi> and being <hi>preſent with</hi> an Enemy, is not relevant to infer a Crime, unleſs it could be made appear, that the Party ſo converſing, and preſent, joyned with the Enemy in <hi>Counſel,</hi> or <hi>Acts of Hoſtility</hi> againſt the State: which is neither libelled nor could be alledged in this Caſe. And as to <hi>Swinton's</hi> having a Sword about him, when he thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to, and converſed with the Enemy; he being a <hi>Gentleman</hi> and a Priſoner upon <hi>Parole,</hi> had liberty to wear his Sword: and his doing ſo, could infer no Crime againſt him, unleſs it had bee libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that he had, whilſt he wore it, uſed it as an Enemy.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:175164:5"/> 4 As the ſaid pretended Decreet proceeds upon frivolous and irrelevant Pretences, and ſo upon that Head falls under the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Article of the CLAIM OF RIGHT; It falls under the ſame Article by the <hi>Defect</hi> of <hi>Probation.</hi> For the ſaid Decreet being a Decrect in <hi>abſence,</hi> neither condeſcends, as to <hi>Swinton,</hi> upon <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> that were examined againſt him, nor upon what they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned,</hi> as all Decreets of this nature (where Parties are not found guilty by their own <hi>Confeſſion</hi>) ought to do: but only bearing, That <hi>the King and Committee of Estates had found the foreſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,</hi> libelled againſt <hi>Swinton, relevant and</hi> SUFFICIENT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY <hi>proven,</hi> without expreſſing <hi>what way</hi> the ſame were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or bearing even ſo much, as that <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were adduced at all in the Probation. Neither is there the leaſt veſtige in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> of Parliament, of any Probation <hi>whatſoever,</hi> led any manner of way againſt <hi>Swinton</hi> in this Matter. So that the whole Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this pretended Decreet, as to <hi>Swinton,</hi> reſolving in the ſimple Aſſertion of a <hi>Clerk,</hi> without any authentick Document of the Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon <hi>Record,</hi> is in Law, no Probation at all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> after he had obtained his Gift of <hi>Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Forfeiture, founded upon the pretended Decreet of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates, 1651. being convinced how groundleſs and illegal the ſaid Decreer was; cauſed raiſe a new Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt <hi>Swinton,</hi> (then a Priſoner in the Tolbooth of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urgh</hi>) before the Parliament 1661. and therein, amongſt other Crimes which he cauſed charge <hi>Swinton</hi> with, he cauſeth libel the very <hi>ſame Crime</hi> in the very <hi>ſame words,</hi> that was libelled againſt him in the Decreet 1651. giving him withall the Deſignation of <hi>John Swinton</hi> OF <hi>SWINTON.</hi> Which was an implicit paſſing from the ſaid Decreet, and a moſt evident Demonſtration that it was then looked upon by him as <hi>no</hi> Decreet. It being obvious both in Law, and common Senſe, that a Man <hi>once</hi> forfeited, cannot be <hi>again</hi> forfeited, ſeing by the <hi>firſt</hi> Forfeiture, in the Conſtruction of <hi>Law,</hi> he is no more in <hi>beeing,</hi> and can have <hi>no</hi> Eſtate to forfeit. Upon all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175164:6"/>which Grounds it is manifeſt, that the ſaid pretended Decreet 1651. is null and void to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
               <p>AND the ſaid Decreet 1651. being <hi>null,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale's</hi> Gift of Forfeiture, as being only founded upon that Decreet, is null, and muſt fall in <hi>conſequence.</hi> Nor can it ſubſiſt by the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſubſequent Decreet of Forfeiture (if any ſuch Decreet had true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been) in the year 1661. becauſe the Gift is anterior to it: the ſaid Gift being dated the 25 of <hi>May</hi> 1661. and the Decreet 1661, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Date the 12 of <hi>July</hi> thereafter. And by the CLAIM OF RIGHT it is declared, <hi>that the diſpoſing of Forfeitures before Sentence, is contrary to Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AND AS TO THE PRETENDED DECREET OF THE PARLIAMENT 1661. The ſame is <hi>null,</hi> and ought to be <hi>reduced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe the ſame proceeds either upon <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>frivolous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,</hi> or upon <hi>Pretences falſe and calumnious,</hi> and is deſtitute of all <hi>Probation</hi> whatſoever. For as to the <hi>firſt</hi> Article of the Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereupon it proceeds, bearing, That <hi>Swinton ſate and voted in the Parliament</hi> 1649. <hi>in which the Act concerning the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment forfeited, and turned out of Office;</hi> It was not relevant. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Man can be, not ever was called in queſtion for ſitting and voting in a Parliament, or-acting therein in a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary</hi> Capacity. Seing what is done by a Parliament, is not to be underſtood the Deed of any <hi>ſingle</hi> Perſon, but of the whole <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Body</hi> of the Nation. And the King did ſo far acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that Parliament 1649. that he admitted Commiſſioners from it, as from the Repreſentatives of the Kingdom. And by his <hi>Treaty</hi> with them, he was obliged to ratifie the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Parliament, after his coming home. Which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly performed by him, in a Parliament held after his Return, in the year 1650. Neither did it appear that <hi>Swinton</hi> voted for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinding the Act in relation to the <hi>Engagement</hi> 1648. nor for the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting,</hi> or <hi>putting out of Office</hi> the Perſons mentioned in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement.</p>
               <p>And as to the <hi>ſecond</hi> Article, bearing <hi>Swinton</hi>'s <hi>holding Correſpondence with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, by writing to, and receiving Letters from him, or by ſending to, and receiving Meſſages from him by word of Mouth;</hi> It was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175164:6"/>denied, and neither was, nor could be proven, it being in it ſelf altogether falſe and calumnious. And whereas in the ſaid ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, it is alledged, as in the firſt Decreet, that <hi>Swinton deſerted his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in the King's Army, and went in to the Enemy;</hi> the former Anſwer to the ſaid firſt Decreet is oppon'd.</p>
               <p>And as to the <hi>thrid</hi> Article, That <hi>Swinton did go along with the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per's Army to</hi> Worceſter, <hi>and fought there againſt the King, at leaſt was with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper there in Arms.</hi> (and which is the onely Crime inſiſted upon by the King's Advocate againſt him;) It was likewiſe denied, as it was <hi>conceived.</hi> For if it could have been made appear, that <hi>Swinton</hi> was at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> he could have inſtructed, that he was there as a <hi>Priſoner</hi> and not as a <hi>Souldier.</hi> Neither could it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been proved, that he acted any thing there in a <hi>hostile</hi> manner. But on the contrary, was ready on all occaſions to ſerve his Countrey, to the utmoſt of his Power in that ſad Conjuncture: In which two of his Brothers in the King's Service, Mr. <hi>Robert Swinton,</hi> who commanded a Troop of Horſe, and Mr. <hi>Alexander</hi> now of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſington,</hi> and one of the Senators of the Colledge of Juſtice, had the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, the firſt of them to be kill'd, and the other taken Priſoner. And the good Offices he did to many of his Countrey Men at that time, it is hoped are not yet forgotten. And if he had been in Arms, as he was not; yet this being a Crime alledged to have been committed in <hi>England,</hi> he was ſecured by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act of <hi>Indemnity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as to the <hi>fourth</hi> Article, that <hi>Swinton did ſit and vote in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in</hi> England, <hi>declaring the King or any other of the Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, incapable to ſucceed in the Royal Government: and as a Reward of his Service, was appointed one of the Commiſſioners for Adminiſtration of Justice, for which he got a conſiderable yearly Sallary out of the puclick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues;</hi> If it could be made appear, that he did ſit and vote in any ſuch Parliament, yet that was no Crime, he being there as one of the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> from <hi>Scotland</hi> after the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION,</hi> and after <hi>the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> were under the Government of the Uſurper, and erected in a <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> And it was <hi>denied</hi> that he was preſent at the paſſing of any Act againſt the King and the Royal Family. And if he had been preſent, as he was not; it was when the Government was in the hands of the Uſurper and Common-wealth; and it fell under the Act
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175164:7"/>of the <hi>Engliſh Indemnity.</hi> And as to his being one of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for <hi>administration of Juſtice,</hi> and having a Sallary for it; He did not accept of that Imployment before the Government was ſettled in the hands of the Uſurper, and Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> to which the whole Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> had then ſubmitted. And it is very well known what good Service in accepting of that Imployment he did to his Countrey: it being the Countrey's Advantage, that ſuch Places of <hi>Truſt,</hi> were in Countreymens hands, rather than in the hands of Strangers, who underſtood nothing of the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of the Kingdom. And as for any Sallary he got thereby, he was never the richer for it: but on the contrary, it is very well known, he was much more in Debt in the year 1660. than he was when he entered upon that Imployment.</p>
               <p>AND as the ſaid pretended Decreet 1661, proceeds upon <hi>frivolous</hi> and <hi>calumnious Pretences,</hi> ſo the ſame is made to proceed upon ſo <hi>lame</hi> a <hi>Probations,</hi> as it is, <hi>without any Probation at all.</hi> For albeit it bear to proceed upon <hi>Swinton</hi>'s <hi>judicial Confeſſion,</hi> there is no ſuch Confeſſion in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Parliament, other than what is contained in the <hi>vvritten Defenſe</hi> given in by him, under his Hand, before the Parliament, which is ſo <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified,</hi> as it could never be a ground of Forfeiture againſt him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſaid pretended Decreet 1661, is <hi>null,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Minutes</hi> on the <hi>Margent</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Inditement,</hi> which are the <hi>Warrants</hi> thereof, are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>forged.</hi> What is evinced from the following grounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſaid Minutes bearing Date 7 <hi>February,</hi> 15 <hi>May,</hi> and 12 <hi>July,</hi> 1661. and ſo being of a conſiderable interval of <hi>Time</hi> one from another, are nevertheleſs written at <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> time; and as by the ſame <hi>Hand,</hi> ſo with the ſame <hi>Pen,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Ink:</hi> and by comparing the Ink wherewith they are written, with that of a Minute on the <hi>foot</hi> of the Inditement, ſigned by the Earl of <hi>Glencairn</hi> as Chancellor, of the ſame <hi>Date</hi> with the firſt of them, <hi>viz.</hi> 7 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1661. (and which is the only <hi>true</hi> Minute extant in the Proceſs) it is evident the Ink of the Minutes on the Margent is a great many years <hi>recenter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> All the three Minutes on the Margent of the Inditement,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175164:7"/>being Signatures of the Procedure of the Parliament, as to this Affair, <hi>in plain Parliament;</hi> the firſt thereof 7 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1661. bears, the then Lord Advocat's <hi>giving in the ſaid Inditement, vvith the former Decreet against</hi> Swinton <hi>(then Pannel) and craving that the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet might be ratified; and</hi> further, <hi>that the ſaid</hi> new <hi>Inditement might be found relevant, and admitted to his Probation;</hi> the King &amp; Eſtates of Parl. are ſaid <hi>to ordain</hi> BEFORE ANSWER, <hi>the new Inditement to be give up to</hi> Swinton, <hi>to ſee and anſwer.</hi> And yet it is evident by the Records of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that the Parliament met not at all <hi>that day,</hi> but only the <hi>Articles.</hi> And by the <hi>true</hi> Minute on the foot of the Inditement, the ſaid 7th. of <hi>February</hi> 1661. the <hi>Lords of the Articles ordained</hi> the ſame thing, which the Minute on the Margent <hi>falſly</hi> ſays, was ordained by the King and Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>viz. that the ſaid Inditment ſhould be given up to John Swinton of that Ilk, to ſee and anſwer;</hi> and as it accordingly was: the Copie thereof under the Advocat's hand, being delivered to <hi>Swinton,</hi> with theſe words at the foot thereof, (written by one <hi>Alexander Reid,</hi> the Advocate's Servant at that time, and ſigned by <hi>Mungo Murray, Ormand</hi> Purſevant) <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 7. <hi>Feberuary</hi> 1661. <hi>It is appointed, that this Inditement be given to</hi> John Swinton, <hi>and he to anſvver up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Tueſday <hi>come a fourtnight, being the</hi> 26 <hi>of this Inſtant.</hi> Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able whereunto, a <hi>Diary</hi> of the Proceedings of that Parliament 1661. written by <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi> one of the preſent Senators of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Juſtice, who was then one of the Clerks of Parliament, bears, that <hi>upon the</hi> 27 February, John Swinton <hi>of that Ilk hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formerly received his Inditement, vvas brought that Day to the Bar, and after his Dittay vvas read, he vvas appointed that day fourtnight to give in his legal Defenſes.</hi> So that it is manifeſt, that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament not ſitting on the 7th of <hi>February,</hi> and <hi>Swinton</hi> that day getting his Inditement (by Order of the Articles,) to anſwer 14 days after; the <hi>firſt</hi> day of his Appearance before the Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved to be the Day mentioned in <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s Diary, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that the ſaid firſt Minute on the Margent of the Inditement 7 <hi>February,</hi> 1661. is altogether falſe. Neither was the <hi>term</hi> made uſe of, [BEFORE ANSWER] either the <hi>Stile</hi> of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175164:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>or indeed of any Court at that time, it being a term introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced long after: nor was it at all in this caſe <hi>intelligible,</hi> it being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that an Inditement could be <hi>conſidered</hi> before it was given up, and <hi>ſeen</hi> by the Party.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thridly,</hi> The ſecond of the ſaid Minutes bearing Date the 15 of <hi>May</hi> 1661. is manifeſt from <hi>ocular inſpecton</hi> to be falſe, and that it and the other two (being writ all at the ſame time) behoved to be forged after the year 1670. For when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that writes the Minutes, was writing the Ciphers of the <hi>Year,</hi> as thinking upon the year wherein the ſaid Minutes were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by him, (which appears by the Earl of <hi>Crawfurd's</hi> Letter, behoved to be the year 1674.) he hath firſt written 167 and the <hi>taking himſelf,</hi> and finding his <hi>miſtake,</hi> he makes the Cipher 7 a 6. and adds the Cipher 1. to it, to make it the year which the Minute behoved to bear, <hi>viz.</hi> 1661. the vitiat Correction ſtanding in the Minute thus, 1661. Into which miſtake, a Man writing <hi>after</hi> the year 1670. might eaſily fall; but it is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Senſe, that no Man could have fallen into ſuch a miſtake, writing <hi>before</hi> the year 1670. 2. By this Minute <hi>May</hi> 15. <hi>Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> is made <hi>appearing and judicially confeſſing that he went with</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel <hi>and his Army to</hi> Worceſter, <hi>and was with him in that Battel;</hi> whereas there was no ſuch judicial Confeſſion made, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>if made,</hi> had been taken under <hi>Swinton's hand,</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribed</hi> by the Preſident of Parliament: neither of which were done. And <hi>Robert Hamilton</hi>'s foreſaid Diary bears only, that the ſaid 15 <hi>of</hi> May, Swinton's <hi>Dittay with his Anſvvers, vvere read before the Parliament in his preſence, and he alſo heard ſpeak verballie for himſelf, and that the Lord Advocate opponed the Dittay, and produced the former Decreet of Forfeiture againſt him,</hi> (which <hi>de facto</hi> was never produc'd till now, tho the <hi>firſt</hi> Minute falſly bear, it was produc'd the 7 <hi>Feb.</hi>) <hi>and which former Decreet the Pannel deſiring to ſee, the Parliament aſſigned him</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>come eight dayes to ſee, and ſay vvhat he could ſay.</hi> Which laſt part, the foreſaid Minute doth alſo bear, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Pannel was ordained to ſee the former Sentence of Forfeiture, and to anſwer</hi> Friday <hi>come eight dayes, being the</hi> 24. <hi>of</hi> May: but with this difference, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute bears, upon the <hi>Pannels</hi> deſiring to ſee the ſaid Decreet, <hi>it was</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:175164:8"/>then <hi>given up to him.</hi> Whereas it is evident by the Copy of the ſaid Decreet, delivered to <hi>Svvinton</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Alexander Reid,</hi> the Advocate's Servant. that it was not delivered to him till the 17 of <hi>May;</hi> it being ſo marked upon the back, with the ſaid <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Reid</hi>'s hand, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was given to <hi>Svvinton</hi> upon the 17. of <hi>May,</hi> to anſwer the 24. By all which it is evident, that <hi>Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> did make no ſuch judicial Confeſſion the foreſaid 15 of <hi>May,</hi> there being no veſtige of it, either under his <hi>own,</hi> or under the <hi>Preſident</hi>'s hand, extant in Proceſs. And it being moſt abſurd, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a <hi>judicial Confeſſion,</hi> which in Criminals is both Proof and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, (ſince <hi>confeſſus pro condemnato habetur,</hi>) that any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Day ſhould be aſſigned to the Pannel for Defenſe. 3. This Minute of the 15 of <hi>May</hi> 1661. ordains <hi>Swinton</hi> to ſee and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, as ſaid is, againſt the 24 of <hi>May.</hi> And yet neither doth the Decreet bear, that <hi>Swinton</hi> was <hi>again</hi> called, nor any thing at all of this Matter of Fact, <hi>that he was ordained to ſee the former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet upon the</hi> 15 <hi>of</hi> May <hi>and to anſwer thereunto againſt the</hi> 24. (which theſe who framed the Decreet, induſtriouſly omit, as foreſeeing the inſerting thereof would have inferr'd a <hi>Nullity</hi> againſt it.) Nor was <hi>Swinton</hi> ever again called, or brought before the Parliament, either that Day, or any time thereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to the thrid and laſt of the ſaid Minutes upon the Margent of the Inditement, which is made to be upon the 12. of <hi>July</hi> 1661. and which is the principal Minute whereupon the pretended De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet of the Parliament 1661. is founded; the <hi>Falſhood</hi> thereof is moſt manifeſt: in that 1. It makes <hi>Swinton compearing</hi> that Day as a <hi>Pannel,</hi> whereas it is certain the did not appear that Day, nor at any time after the 15. of <hi>May.</hi> 2. By this Minute not only the foreſaid pretended Decreet of the Committee of Eſtates 1651. is <hi>ratified,</hi> but <hi>Swinton</hi> is declared <hi>of new guilty of the Crime of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, upon his judicial Confeſſion.</hi> And yet there is no ſuch judicial Confeſſion extant, nor was there ever any ſuch Confeſſion made by him, but what was ſo qualified as <hi>cleared</hi> him 3. It makes the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ratifie the ſaid pretended Decreet 1651. without his being <hi>heard</hi> upon his <hi>Defenſe</hi> againſt the ſame, tho a Day was aſſigned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175164:9"/>to him for that effect. 4. The ſaid Minute has none of the Solemnities of a Sentence of Forfeiture for Treaſon, ſeing it does not bear, READ, VOTED, TOUCHED <hi>with the Scepter,</hi> or any Warrant for <hi>Publication</hi> by ſound of <hi>Trumpet,</hi> or for <hi>tearing of Arms:</hi> which are the <hi>ordinary</hi> and <hi>indiſpenſable</hi> Solemnities in uſe to be adhibited, in the pronouncing of Sentences and Dooms of Forfeiture in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the <hi>Signatures</hi> of which Sentences and Dooms of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, after the <hi>voting</hi> and <hi>touching</hi> thereof, as always written upon a Paper apart, <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the Proceſs, and <hi>ſigned</hi> by the <hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> or <hi>Preſident</hi> of Parliament, and what is punctually obſerved inall the Forfeitures <hi>truely</hi> paſs'd in this Parliament, as is evident from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords. No ſuch thing being to be found in <hi>Swinton's</hi> Caſe: what doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly would not have been omitted, if any Doom of Forfeiture had truely paſſed, by VOTE of Parliament, againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> All the ſaid three Minutes are ſubſcribed by the late Earl of <hi>Crawford,</hi> as Preſident of the Parliament 1661. with theſe Letters ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to his Subſcription, <hi>J. P. D. P.</hi> as if ſubſcribed by him in that Parliament, <hi>in praeſentia Dominorum Parliamenti:</hi> and the Earl's Letter, which a litle before his Death he wrote to the deceaſs'd <hi>Swinton,</hi> in the year 1674. diſcovers not only that they were not <hi>ſigned</hi> by him till <hi>then,</hi> which was 13 years after, but that they were not ſo much as <hi>written</hi> till that time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the Earl being a Perſon of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> as he was known to be, his Teſtimony alone in this matter of Fact (ſo ingenuouſly declaring the manner how he was prevailed with to ſign the ſaid Minutes at that time (and what <hi>ſcruples</hi> he had againſt the doing thereof, when he did it) is ſufficient if there were no more, to convell the truth of theſe Minutes, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Demonſtration to the world, of their Forgery; and what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Methods were taken at that time-to perpetuat the Ruine of ſo antient a Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> And yet there is this further, and which is an Argument un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable of the <hi>falſhood</hi> of the ſaid Minutes, whereupon the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Decreet of the Parliament 1661 is founded. That after they were thus made up by <hi>Hayſtoun</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Crawſurd</hi>'s Subſcription impetrat thereunto in the manner narrated in his Lordſhip's Letter,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175164:9"/>Sir <hi>Archibald Primeroſe</hi> the then Clerk Regiſter thought himſelf not <hi>in tuto</hi> to give any Extract therof under his Hand to the Duke of <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdale,</hi> till upon a Petition given in by the Duke to the Lords of Seſſion, bearing, that the ſaid Sir <hi>Archibald</hi> ſcrupled <hi>to give any ſuch Extract,</hi> he was ordained by them to do the ſame: it being impoſſible to imagin ſo knowing a man as Sir <hi>Archibald Primeroſe</hi> was, could have any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon to ſcruple at the doing of a thing of this nature, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the duety of his Office oblig'd him, (eſpecially to a Man of ſuch Power as the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> then was,) unleſs it had been that he was conſcious to himſelf of the falſhood of thoſe Minutes, which to gratifie the Duke, he had perſwaded the Earl of <hi>Crawfurd</hi> to ſign ſo many years after the Parliament 1661.</p>
               <p>FROM ALL WHICH, it is evident upon how <hi>lame</hi> and <hi>defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> a Title the Eſtate of <hi>Swinton</hi> hath been poſſeſs'd by the late Duke and this Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> theſe 30 years by paſt. The pretended De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet of the Committee of Eſtatees 1651. whereupon the Duke obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Gift, having proceeded upon ſuch <hi>vveak</hi> Pretences, and <hi>defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Probation, and look'd upon as ſo <hi>inſignificant,</hi> that it was <hi>paſs'd from</hi> by Intenting of a <hi>nevv</hi> Inditement for the <hi>ſame</hi> Crime, before the Parliament 1661. And albeit a Sentence neither <hi>did,</hi> nor <hi>could</hi> paſs upon that Inditement (after a <hi>Term</hi> was aſſigned by the Parliament for a <hi>further Hearing</hi>) till <hi>Svvinton</hi> had been FURTHER HEARD, which he <hi>never vvas;</hi> a Decreet nevertheleſs is made up on <hi>falſe Minutes,</hi> as paſs'd in that Parliament, <hi>ratifying</hi> the former Decreet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and <hi>forfeiting</hi> him of <hi>new,</hi> (which are <hi>terms inconſiſtent</hi> in Law.) And neither the Duke of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> nor this Earl, having the leaſt <hi>colour</hi> to juſtifie ſo horrid a <hi>vvrong,</hi> or the <hi>oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>hardſhip</hi> the deceaſs'd <hi>Swinton</hi> and his Children have been thereby <hi>expoſed</hi> to during ſo long a tract of time, with the <hi>loſs</hi> his lawful <hi>Creditors</hi> have thereby <hi>ſutain'd;</hi> except the ſole Pretence of <hi>Swinton</hi>'s having poſſeſs'd a part of the Eſtate of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> during a few years of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, tho the yearly Rent therof was far within <hi>one half</hi> of the yearly Rent of the Eſtate of <hi>Swinton:</hi> and as to which this <hi>Svvinton,</hi> who now inſiſts for Recover of his Father's Inheritance, being content to allow
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175164:10"/>all that ever his Father intrometted with of the Eſtate of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> the firſt end of the Earl and his Brother's Intromiſſion with the Eſtate of <hi>Svvinton</hi> (which will be of ten times a greater value;) IT IS HOPED the PARLIAMENT <hi>ex Justitia,</hi> will REDUCE the ſaid two pretended <hi>Decreets,</hi> and <hi>Gift</hi> of <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> with all that he followed thereupon, and <hi>RESTORE</hi> the <hi>Swinton IN INTEGR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> againſt the ſame.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
